Alrighty, so now that we have our local development environment set up, in this video,
we're going to be looking at the basics of using Visual Studio Code while setting up
a template project.
So a template project is a great way to get started.
It allows us to link our style sheet and our script file, as well as some other resources
like font awesome icons and a favicon, things that we're most likely to need on every
single project, and it allows us to then copy that template and paste it and then rename
it, and then we're not starting from scratch every time we want to start a new project.
Okay, so let's get started.
You can see on the desktop that I have a code folder here, so we're going to click on that,
and you'll notice that there's already an icon in this folder.
We'll get to that in a few minutes, but first I'm going to right click and I'm going
to create a new folder and I'm going to call it dash dash space and then template.
So the reason I am naming it with two dashes at the start is so that if we are sorting
this folder alphabetically, it is always going to be at the top.
Okay, so we can close this now and we're going to open visual studio code, so I'm going
to use command space bar and I'm going to type visual and you see it pops up here.
It's actually still in our downloads folder, which is fine and we're going to click on
it to open it and I'll make it full page.
Okay, so we're going to land on this welcome page here and you can see it has some suggestions
on how to start and I'm going to go ahead and click open and you can see that.
This is already inside my code folder and I'm going to go ahead and I'm going to click
on the dash dash template folder and then I'm going to click open.
Okay, so now we're in our template and yes, we're going to allow it to access files
on our desktop and yes, I'm going to check this always trust the authors, yes, I trust
the author because the author is me.
Okay, and you can see right here on the explorer that we're in our dash dash template
folder and the first thing we're going to do, we can actually close this, we're going
to create a few files here.
So we're going to click on this icon here, we see when we hover over it says new file,
we're going to click on that and we're going to start by creating our index dot HTML
and you'll see that it opens that file there.
Then we're going to create a style dot CSS, so this is going to be our CSS file and then
we're also going to create a script dot JS file and this is our JavaScript file.
Okay, and you can see it has all three open here.
Now we're going to start with our index HTML file.
So the very first thing we're going to do is we're going to set the doc type as HTML,
which is good practice to do, we're going to use our bracket and you see that it actually
is the very first suggestion, so we're going to go ahead and click on that and it does the
rest for us.
Okay, very handy.
So that's one great thing about Visual Studio Code is right out of the box, it has a lot
of cool auto complete stuff for us, similar to what exists as well on Code pen.
So now we're going to need to create our HTML element, our head element and our body element.
But we have a handy shortcut for this, we're just going to type doc DOC and you can see
it's an Emmett abbreviation and then we can go ahead and press enter and you'll see that
it creates our HTML element, it sets our languages English, it creates our head and our
body and our closing tags and it also creates a few meta tags as well as a title for our
page.
Awesome, so that gives us a nice little head start there.
The next thing we're going to do is we need to actually link our CSS file and our JavaScript
file to our HTML file in order for them to actually work.
So to do this, we're going to start with our style sheet and below our title here, we're
going to type out link and then we're going to go ahead and press tab and by default,
it's going to add the attribute of rel as style sheet here and our href, we're just going
to go ahead and start typing style and you'll see that it comes up here and I can just
go ahead and click on it and it'll finish the rest for me and that is our style CSS, we're
just writing it like this because it's actually within the same folder.
If it was in a different folder, we would need to use slightly different syntax but in
this case, it's in the same folder.
Next, we're going to add a link to our JavaScript file, we're actually going to do this
inside of our body and we're going to use comments first, so we're going to use command
question mark and then we're going to just type script or control question mark on windows
and then we're going to type script and you see again, has some abbreviations for us
and we can go ahead and type this script source and it adds the source attribute for
us.
Same thing, we're going to type SC and you can see it pops up here and I can actually
just press enter to add our script.js link, okay.
So we've linked our style sheet as well as our script file.
Awesome.
So next, we're going to want to do a few other things.
First, we're going to be adding font awesome icons to our project.
This is something that is very useful because you'll normally use things like social media
icons on your portfolio or if it's a website you're creating for a business, it's very
handy to have font awesome icons in your project, okay.
So we're going to jump over to the browser to take a look at this.
So again, I'm going to provide a link for this exact page.
So this is going to be using font awesome version five.
They are currently on version six, but I prefer using version five because it requires just
a style sheet to work whereas the newer ones require a JS file and need to sign up for that.
So to me, this implementation is a little bit simpler and you can see that if we scroll
down here, I've also filtered on free and there's over 1500 free icons that you're
able to use, have a lot of different examples here and it's perfect for social media icons.
So for example, I have a GitHub icon here, okay, so we'll come back to this in a moment
to access this with just the style sheet that is hosted externally.
We're going to go to another website.
This is a content delivery network, JS website.
So that's what CDN stands for content delivery network and we're going to go ahead and
click on, or we're going to actually copy this link here so you can use command C to copy
this.
Again, I will provide a link to this in the course as well.
And we're going to jump back over to Visual Studio Code and we're going to add this style sheet
actually above our style.css and we're going to do the same thing link, press tab, it's
the style sheet again and we're going to do command V to paste it in here.
You can see now that this is a bit long and it's actually stretched out our page here.
So we can actually fix that by using alt and Z and that is going to word wrap.
So you can see here that line seven and then we have a gap here.
So it's technically one line, but now we can actually see the full line it actually is
wrapping to the next line so that everything is visible.
This is very helpful, especially when you have a paragraph that has a lot of text in it
and then you'll be able to actually see the whole paragraph.
Okay, so we're going to go back to our browser and actually before we do that we're going
to go to our desktop and we're actually going to open up our code folder and we're going
to open up our template folder and you can see that we actually have the three files
here that we created and we're going to go ahead and we're actually going to open our
index HTML file so that we can actually see the project that we're working on and you
can see that it has the document title here but right now we're not actually seeing anything.
So the reason I wanted to open this is because we want a test to make sure that our font
awesome style sheet is working and to do that we're going to need to use an icon, try
to use an icon and we're going to go with the GitHub icon and if we scroll down and we
click you see that it's going to copy that code snippet and then we're going to go back
to Visual Studio code and we're going to go ahead and we're just going to paste it in the
body here.
You can see that this is saving by default and that is actually because I have auto save
enabled so this is an enabled by default but I have it enabled so every time I make a change
it is automatically saving all of my files which is very handy.
Okay, so we're going to go back to Edge and we're going to go to our project and if I refresh
this you can see we have a very very small GitHub icon that's because we haven't added
any styling to it but if I zoom in on the page you can see that yeah we have a GitHub
icon here okay perfect so that means our fun awesome style sheet is working next we're
going to look at favicons so what is a favicon so if you don't know what that is it is
actually this little icon that you're seeing on the tab here so you see there's one
for CSS tricks there's one for our CDN there's one for fun awesome but if you look at
our project it just has this blank page here so in my opinion a favicon is always an
important thing to add to her project as I do think it makes it look a lot more professional
than if you just leave it blank so that's why I'm talking about it so early on so there's
this great article here on CSS tricks dot com and it allows you to actually use an external
link for a favicon so you don't even actually need to have a file so as a fair warning
this might not work in the future it is using a feature of Google so essentially Google
is indexing all of these favicons and this is what is allowing us to use them but it
might not always work though it is working for now we're going to go ahead and we're
going to copy this link here and we're going to go back to our code and we're going
to go above this style sheet here I can actually also close this explore to have a little
bit more space by just clicking on the icon there and I'm going to comment a title for
this and this is going to be grab favicon from Google and I'm also going to add a little
bit of a warning might be unsupported in the future okay and we're going to go ahead and
we're going to add a link again so link and then we're going to press tab this time
though it's actually not going to be a style sheet it's going to be an icon and we're
also going to add a type to specify the type of icon it is and that's going to be equal
to image slash PNG and then for a trap we're going to go ahead and paste that in there
but instead of using CSS dash tricks I'm going to actually use my own website you can
use any domain you like you could use code pen.io or whatever you like but I'm going
to use my own website justinto.design okay and I'm going to actually pick a comment
for this while I'm at it for an awesome version 5 okay and this is already saved automatically
again that's one of the great features of Visual Studio code and we're going to go back
to our browser and I'm going to go ahead and refresh the page and you can see that
we have our icon here it's a little J that is my favicon okay cool so that is working
so that's one way you can add a favicon to your template and what we're going to do
though is actually add a file the file that you saw in the very beginning of this video
so we're actually going to comment this out so that is one way to do it just by having
this link and then grabbing a favicon but the other way is to just link to a local file
and so that's what we're going to do here and we're going to comment out a title for
this so this is going to be our zero to mastery favicon and we're going to have another
link and again not a style sheet it's going to be an icon and again our type is going
to be equal to image/png and then our ref so we actually have to copy this into our template
folder so now it's inside of our folder and now we're going to have just type FA press
enter and it does the rest for us and we're also going to change this title while we're
added this title is going to be template okay and we're going to go back to our browser
and we're going to refresh and you see we have our zero to mastery icon there okay
very cool now there's a few more little things we're going to do here we're going to
remove our font awesome we're going to talk about that more in the future but we're actually
going to add some default styling so we're going to have a very small amount of default
styling so we're going to target our HTML element so that's another way of targeting everything
and we're going to use the box sizing and you can see it actually offers some suggestions
again this is very handy and we actually want the first one border box so we're going
to do that press enter and what this does is when you add padding or margin or a border
to an element that has a width it actually adds the padding margin border on top of that
and actually doubles it because usually you have it on both the left and the right or the
top and the bottom so it's actually going to double whatever those values are add them
all together and what this does is it essentially bypasses that in a way because it will
actually decrease the total width of your element so let's say that your element was 100 pixels
wide and you had a 10 pixel padding and a 10 pixel margin so it's going to add the left
and right padding and then the left and right margin so 10 times 2 is 20 and then again
is 20 because they're equal so that would be 140 would become your width instead of 100
so when you have box sizing border box your width will actually stay at 100 and it will
actually shrink the content of your element to compensate the good thing about this is
that it actually prevents the horizontal scroll bar that you might have at the bottom
of your page that to me doesn't look good it's nice to just have that nice vertical
scroll bar okay and the next thing we're going to do is on our body element we're going
to remove the margin that is on our body by default we're going to set it to zero on all
four sides we're going to add margin when we need to on specific elements rather than
having margin by default and then the last thing we're going to do is we're going to
add a min height value of 100 VH V4 height so we want the minimum height of our project
to always be the size of our browser window at minimum so I'm going to illustrate this
by adding a background dash color and we're going to make it dodger blue you see it
even as suggestions for named colors which is great and we're going to go back to our
browser and I'm going to refresh and you see that everything is blue we have no vertical
scroll bar and we have no horizontal scroll bar but it is taking up 100% of the height
of the page with our VH 100 VH okay cool so that's basically it for our template we're
going to go ahead and remove the background color want it to be as plain as possible but
this is going to be a great starting point for our future projects one of the very quick
thing I'm going to show you that is very useful that I use all the time is if you see
here there's an icon that allows me to split the editor so when I click on that you can
see that now I have two styles CSS files and this is very handy when you're doing mobile
responsive styling so your media queries and your style sheet might actually be very long
it might be several hundred lines long and you can have one side at the very bottom doing
your media queries and you can have the other side up above that's looking at your
main styling and seeing how you're going to need to alter that or you could also just
have your HTML file along with your CSS file usually I would drag this so my CSS file is
a little bit smaller but you can see that also because we're word wrapping we're still
able to actually see everything in our HTML file including these longer links you can
see that we have devil lines here okay so those are the very basics of visual studio
code in the next one we're going to dive in to actually installing some extensions for
visual studio code which is going to supercharge our productivity even further all right
I'll see you in that one bye for now